Hope everybody hope everybody's staying safe with the hurricane. We are today's
דף ס"ג daf Samech Gimmel 63 and we're continuing discussing the kosher
and the non-kosher birds.
We had yesterday looked at the idea with what the גמרא, Gemara,
it was a complicated גמרא Gemara two days ago, but the upshot
seems to be that any bird with all four, with none of
the kosher סימנים, simanim, or said another way, the four non-kosher סימנים
simanim is definitely not kosher. One example of that being the נץ,
netz, excuse me, the נשר, nesher, the eagle or probably the vulture,
and then going on to make them with all of the four
kosher סימנים simanim it definitely is kosher and some with some mix
of kosher and non-kosher סימנים simanim that would depend on whether it
was on the list or not. And that continued yesterday with analysis
of searching particular, very, very particular birds and whether they were kosher
or not kosher if you had a question which was only one
or two kosher סימנים, simanim, if you could eliminate certain things from
the list, if you could assume therefore that you were looking at
a kosher bird. The upshot being that with all four kosher סימנים
simanim you could assume it was kosher, and that can be very
relevant for questions today. However, a point at the very end was
the גמרא Gemara talked about a certain thing called the hen of
the swamp, תרנגולתא דאגמא, tarniegolta de-agma, where they had assumed it was
kosher and then they found that it actually was a bird of
prey, that it had preyed on animals, something that they had not
seen before, and they reversed their decision and said that it was
not kosher. And based on this, the גמרא Gemara says that in
like one sentence, but based on this רש"י Rashi says that we
cannot eat any bird without a מסורת mesorah because any bird that
we think might be kosher and might have all four kosher סימנים,
simanim, since one of those סימנים simanim is that it is not
a bird of prey, we might later discover that it is a
bird of prey and therefore we cannot rely on what we have
seen and we need a very particular מסורת. mesorah. This again is
not explicit in the גמרא Gemara at all and raises the question
about New World birds like turkey where there really was no מסורת
mesorah for, and even within רש"י Rashi's statement, is it really absolute
or if you have a very wide and broad set
of data about it over many years and hundreds of years even,
is it really true that you need a מסורת mesorah if you
can really prove that it is not a דורס? dores? That being
said, one of our participants yesterday did say that wild turkeys actually
do eat rats and field mice and so on, so it remains
also a question about how you define דורס, dores, but it is
not maybe as simple as we might have thought. Anyway, those were
the discussions yesterday and one other final point of that, which is
to go again to this issue about the what do you call
it,
the issue about being a bird of prey is that the גמרא
Gemara is never really explicit about how that weighs vis-a-vis these other
סימנים, simanim, although a few times it does mention you can trust
this if it's not a bird of prey, they discovered it was
a bird of prey, but it's not so clear. תוספות, Tosafot, and
based on some of the earlier discussion, it could sound that it
would be theoretically possible that a kosher bird would be a bird
of prey. תוספות Tosafot however is very clear and takes a line
from the משנה Mishna that says that says there that there is
no bird of prey that is not that every bird of prey
is non-kosher
or is not kosher and takes that to be a categorical statement.
So for תוספות, Tosafot, if it's a bird of prey it's definitely
not kosher, but if it is not a bird of prey and
some has some of the other non-kosher סימנים, simanim, then it depends
if it is on the list. Okay, so that's quick review from
yesterday and again that last point about a bird of prey was
revising a point I had made on Friday where I had suggested
where based on the גמרא Gemara one could have suggested otherwise. But
anyway, for תוספות Tosafot it is definitely not kosher if it is
a bird of prey. Okay, so we now continue with the גמרא,
Gemara, ס"ג עמוד א', Samech Gimmel amud aleph, the second line from
the top. אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said, שקיטנא אריכי שוקי וסומקי שרי. shakitna arichi shaki vesumki shari.
So this bird called a שקיטנא shakitna
and it depends on whether it is a kosher or non-kosher species
depends on the following indicators: if it has long legs, literally long
thighs, אריכי שוקי, arichi shaki, וסומקי vesumki
and it's red, שרי shari it's permissible. וסימנך Vesimancha and the way
to remember that is מורזמא מורזמא, murzma murzma,
that מורזמא murzma which is a name of a kosher bird that
they were familiar with which had which was reddish and long legs
and therefore since it looks similar to that, not because, but this
is just a mnemonic of a way to remember it. גוצי
וסומקי gutzei vesumki if it however has short legs even though it's
reddish, אסירי assiri it's forbidden. וסימנך Vesimancha the way to remember this
is ננוס פסול. nanos pasul. A midget is invalid to do the
עבודה Avodah the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's considered a מום, Mum,
something, a physical defect, and therefore here something that's if this bird
is short, legs are short, it's a way to remember. Again these
are not reasons, these are memory aids, these are mnemonics.
אריכי שקי וירוקי, Arichi shakei veyeroki, let's say it has long legs
but it is either green or yellow, depending on what the word
ירוק yarok means in different contexts, אסורה Asura that is forbidden. וסימנך,
Vesimanchah, the way to remember it is ירוקין פסולין. Yerokin pesulin. If
you remember before we had if a bird fell into the fire
and the inner organs turned reddish or yellowish, excuse me greenish or
yellow, it is invalid, it's a טריפה, treifa, so here again we
learned that that color is—and this is not the reason but a
mnemonic—that that color is a problem. Okay now again the question here
always is that are these really different species or not? Some of
these things might seem to be simple variations of a species, and
how the גמרא Gemara determines you know what defines a species for
these characteristics. Also one has to wonder, right since that presumably the
difference here is whether it has these סימנים simanim or not, is
it really possible that with—within you
know birds that have these similar characteristics and these slight variations, unless
they are genuinely different species, is it really possible that some of
these traits are different? Unless of course the answer is or the
possibility is that maybe some of them would be birds of prey
in some way and some would not, like wild species, not wild
species, not really clear. Also let's remember that the גמרא Gemara did
say that if it has some of the כשר סימנים kosher simanim,
and some of the non-כשר, kosher it depends if it's on the
list and that would depend on what its name is, so just
whether it has the name of what's on the list and maybe
these differences would determine whether it is included in the name on
the list. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Now the גמרא
Gemara is actually going to go through and look at some of
the birds mentioned in the תורה Torah and try to give us
descriptions of them. And here of course the big challenge is that
do we—can we really truly identify them?
Because it is so critical as we've just seen, unless it has
all the כשר kosher, סימנים, simanim if it doesn't have all of
them we really need to know what's on the list. So we've
already started mentioning the נשר, nesher, which again we always assume means
the eagle, but as Felix said, Yehuda Felix in his great book
about the flora and fauna in the תורה Torah and he has
similar books on the משנה, Mishnah, he identifies it with the with
the griffon vulture. Here's a picture of it, I don't know if
you can see.
There's the griffon vulture.
And has a lot to do
with a number of indicators really proves that it
is—that it is what the תורה Torah is referring to as נשר
nesher and it is the largest bird found in ישראל. Yisrael.
Okay so let's take—anyway let's take a look now at the other
ones that the גמרא Gemara discusses. Okay,
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, שלך, Shalach, how about the שלך?
Shalach? זה
השולה דגים מן הים. Zeh hasholeh dagim min hayam. So the first
two letters of של, shal, it's saying that this is one that
scoops up fish from the ocean. Now what would that be? So
again I'll tell you what Felix says it is—he says actually it
is a fish owl, quite interestingly. There's his picture of it, a
fish owl.
Whoops, that's the wrong one, sorry. Fish owl, there you go.
It's also—others have identified it with other types of birds that scoop
things up like a like a pelican. Let me actually show you
a good place where you have a discussion of this.
Artscroll, as I indicated, both here and in its—and in its English
translation of the תורה Torah refuses to translate because they don't want
to mislead people in terms of the הלכה halacha interpretation. Aryeh Kaplan
in The Living Torah, which is a fabulously underappreciated translation which has
you know excellent in terms of the notes and the depth that
he gives for different—for different sections of translation. Anyway here's what he
has about this. Let me just turn to it.
There we go. So here for example are some of the pictures
in this section in ויקרא. Vayikra.
And he
says—so—he does interestingly translate נשר nesher as eagle, but in the—in the
footnote points out that it is probably not that. Now
for the שלך Shalach he says that that is the cormorant,
which is a bird that catches fish from the sea. And here
is a picture of a cormorant.
The second bird here. Okay, so anyway, that is the שלך. Shalach.
All right, so let's continue. So שלך דשלה דגים מן הים. Shalach
deshaleh dagim min hayam. דוכיפת, Duchifat, what is the דוכיפת? Duchifat? So
שהודו כפות Shehodo kaffut that its glory or its crown of feathers
is bent over.
So that might be the hoopoe, never heard of it before, but
anyway it's got a nice crown of feathers and it can fold
it in and fold it out. So some say that's what's being
referred to here. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly,
דוכיפת שהודו כפות. Duchifat shehodo kaffut. וזה שהביא שמיר לבית המקדש. V'zeh
sheheivi shamir l'Beis HaMikdash. There was a story in גיטין Gittin about
how they needed the שמיר, shamir, this type of a worm that
could cut through rock,
and the way they got it, they needed it for the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash because you're not allowed to use iron tools to
use the stones. And the way they did it is
they got it from the דוכיפת Duchifat because the דוכיפת Duchifat used
this שמיר shamir for it to break stones in order that it
could get its prey inside stones. And actually אונקלוס Onkelos in translating
דוכיפת Duchifat translated as the breaker of stones. Okay, so that's the
דוכיפת, Duchifat, whatever that is, presumed the hoopoe maybe.
And let me tell you what what's his name translates it as,
Slifkin translates it as...
Yeah,
the
hoopoe, he has a nice bigger picture, bigger than Kaplan, you can
see it's got a crown of feathers on the top.
Okay, now we go on. רבי יוחנן כי הוי חזי שלך, Rabbi
Yochanan ki havei chazi shalach, when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saw this
שלך, shalach, this bird that caught fish, whichever it might be, cormorant,
אמר משפטיך
תהום רבה, amar mishpatecha tehom raba, your judgments are in the great
depths. כי הוי חזי נמלה, Ki havei chazi nemala, when he saw
an ant, אמר צדקתך כהררי אל, amar tzidkascha k'harrei Eil, your righteousness
is like the mountains of God. Now what does this mean? So
רש״י Rashi has two explanations. One is that it means
that the fish are subject to the judgment of God even though
they are תהום רבה tehom raba in the great
depths, they will be, they also are judged.
So fish that do wrong, which is a strange concept, but anyway,
or maybe it's just to say fish whose time it is to
die, this cormorant swoops in and takes them even though they live
in the depths, so nobody escapes the judgment of God. And the
ant, God's righteousness is like the great mountains
because
because even the ants,
because God even, you know, even gives life to the ants and
supports the ants even though they are very tiny. That's one explanation.
The other explanation רש״י Rashi says that he prefers, that first one
is from his teachers. The second explanation he prefers is that God's
judgment is to the great depths, which means that God,
let me just look at רש״י Rashi again,
right, that God, it's not about the fish but it's about the
cormorant which makes more sense, that God, you know, gives it what
it needs but it's more of a sense of justice because משפט,
mishpat, it's a sense of justice because it has to really work
for it and it has to really,
you know, swoop into the ocean. It doesn't get it easy. But
ants have their food in a more easily, you know, they just
raid a picnic or something. So that's not as much God's משפט,
mishpat, that's more God's צדקה, tzedaka, righteousness or you know charity, although
it is funny use of the word צדקה tzedaka because צדק tzedek
is probably you know the more original sense of the word צדקה
tzedaka which is not that different from משפט, mishpat, צדק משפט tzedek
mishpat usually are you
know are jointed words. All right, now we continue.
אמר מימר, Amar Meimar, לקני וביטני שריין. likni u'bitni sharyin. These types
of, we're back to listing kosher non-kosher birds, we're no longer identifying
the ones in the תורה. Torah. So these birds called לקני likni
and ביטני bitni are kosher birds.
שיקנאי וביטנאי, Shiknai u'bitnai, how about those birds? So
מקום שנהגו לאכול אוכלין, makom shenahagu le'echol ochlin, in a place where
it's a custom to eat these birds you can eat them. מקום
שנהגו שלא לאכול אין אוכלין, makom shenahagu shelo le'echol ein ochlin, if
it's not a custom to eat them you're not allowed to eat
them. So sounds like we don't know, follow your custom. To which
the גמרא Gemara says אטו, atu, what do you mean? במנהגא תליא
מילתא? Beminhaga talya milsa? Is it based on a custom? It sounds
like you know it's not really an issue of kosher or טרפה,
treifa, it's just a question of what your custom is, but you
know this is a real הלכה halacha question. So the גמרא Gemara
says אין, in, yes it is based on a custom, ולא קשיא,
v'lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא באתרא דשכיח פרס ועזניה, Ha b'asra
d'shchiach peras v'ozniya, הא באתרא דלא שכיח פרס ועזניה. ha b'asra d'lo
shchiach peras v'ozniya. The question is is the פרס peras and the
עזניה, ozniya, these two birds that we said before are not common
in the ישוב, yishuv, are not common you know in inhabitable places,
which again what's his name Slifkin identifies them as two variations of
the, let me just find
them.
So, also the נשר nesher the vulture, but okay. Anyway, so these
two types are not found in habitable places, and therefore you can
usually don't have to worry about them. You can usually assume that
if a bird has only one kosher סימן, siman, the worst the
only thing it could be is פרס ועזניה, peres ve-ozniya, and because
they're not found in habitable places or if you know to exclude
them, it's not a problem. So here the גמרא Gemara is saying
in a similar way that if there is a place where פרס
ועזניה peres ve-ozniya are common, then you might have to not eat
them because maybe these you're thinking that they are these other birds,
but maybe they really are the פרס והעזניה. peres ve-ha-ozniya. So therefore,
and since they all have one non-kosher one kosher סימן, siman, you
have to be concerned that maybe this is you you're making a
mistake and this is the פרס ועזניה. peres ve-ozniya. However, if it
is a place where פרס ועזניה peres ve-ozniya are not common, הא
באתרא דלא שכיח פרס ועזניה, ha be-atra de-lo shechiach peres ve-ozniya, so
there's no reason to be concerned that this thing which looks to
be this kosher מין min is anything other than what the kosher
מין min presents itself to be and it is kosher. Now what
did the גמרא Gemara mean before when it said, oh, how could
this really be based on a custom? I mean, haven't we said
at the beginning when I was summing up yesterday's דף daf that
according to רש״י, Rashi, some place you know if you have doubts
or whatever or maybe all birds can only be you know רש״י
Rashi is really saying after the time of the גמרא, Gemara, but
anyway all birds
certainly can be and might required to be eaten based on a
מסורה? mesorah? So maybe that's what it's saying: one place had a
מסורה, mesorah, the other place did not have a מסורה. mesorah. So
some of the ראשונים Rishonim deal with it and they say, no,
because if one place had a מסורה mesorah then we could rely
on that מסורה mesorah then everybody should be able to eat it
on the back of the מסורה mesorah of this one place that
is saying that they have this tradition. So the fact that it
said some places do not eat it seems to say that it
was more than just a question of did they have a מסורה
mesorah or not. Okay, so now we continue. So these are kosher
species, but you cannot eat them in a place where they might
be confused with non-kosher species. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. Now אביי Abaye
says again going on to lists of kosher birds or non-kosher birds,
not leaving the identifying those in the תורה. Torah.
So says אביי, Abaye, קואי וכקואי אסירי. kuai ve-kakuai asiri.
So birds called קואי kuai and כקואי kakuai are forbidden. כקואתא שריא.
kakuasa sharya. The כקואתא kakuasa is however permissible, whatever these birds are.
במערבא Be-maarava and in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מלקו עלה. malku aleih.
But in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
although I just got through saying that this כקואתא kakuasa is permissible,
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they believe that it is not only
forbidden but so definitely forbidden that they even give lashes. So here
we also see interesting that a radical difference about a particular bird:
some believing it was totally kosher, some believing it was totally forbidden.
Was that a question about whether it had סימנים simanim or not?
Then you would think that there wouldn't be such a debate. So
presumably it was an issue that some of them and did not
have others, and was a question about whether it was on the
list that's in the תורה. Torah. דקרו ליה תחווצא. Dekaru leh tachvasa.
In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they say it's forbidden, they also call
it a תחווצא. tachvasa. And maybe their different naming also had something
to do with assuming it was on the list. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. Now we're going back to the פסוקים pesukim in the תורה.
Torah. תנשמת. Tinshemet. So this is one of the forbidden birds, the
תנשמת. tinshemet.
באות שבעופות. ba'ut she-be-ofot. It is the באות ba'ut of birds. Now
what does that mean? And what is a תנשמת? tinshemet? So רש״י
Rashi variously translates the תנשמת, tinshemet, even here in the גמרא, Gemara,
either as an owl or as a bat. He's more inclined to
think that it's a bat. Now באות שבעופות ba'ut she-be-ofot might mean
a bird that howls or shrieks, which could explain or hoots, which
could explain it being a bat or an owl. It's also possible
that the that the correct גרסא girsa here is בבעות שבעופות be-vavat
she-be-ofot because the אונקלוס, Unkelos, the Aramaic of this word תנשמת tinshemet
is בבעות bava'at with the vav and the aleph reversed. Okay, so
anyway that is what the תנשמת tinshemet is. Now there's an interesting
point that the word תנשמת tinshemet also appears in the list of
non-kosher שרצים, sheratzim, like rodents. So let's take a look. So
ברייתא Baraita says, אתה אומר באות שבעופות, atomer ba'ut she-be-ofot, you say
this word תנשמת tinshemet that appears in the list of non-kosher birds
is talking about this screecher of the birds. או אינו אלא באות
שבשרצים, O eino ella ba'ut she-ba-sheratzim, maybe it's a similar type of
a screecher or similar type of an animal amongst the non-kosher rodents
because it also appears in that list? אמרת צא ולמד מי״ג מדות
שהתורה נדרשת בהן. Amarta tze u-lmad mi-yod gimmel middot she-ha-Torah nidreshet bahen.
Go learn from the classic hermeneutical rules, the 13 hermeneutical rules. Which
are they? דבר הלמד מעניינו. davar ha-lamed me-inyano. The most obvious one
being that you define things based on context. So context tells you
what we're talking about. So therefore, דבר הלמד מעניינו, davar ha-lamed me-inyano,
במה הכתוב מדבר? be-meh hakatuv medabber? בעופות. Be-ofot.
Right now we're in the context of birds. So if we're in
the context of birds, אף כאן בעופות. af kan be-ofot.
The תנשמת tinshemet is a type of a bird. תניא נמי הכי
גבי שרצים. Tanya nami hachi gabbi sheratzim. And we talk similarly by
the rodents, except in the opposite way. כי האי גוונא. Ki hai
gavna. תנשמת, Tinshemet, what is— תנשמת, tinshemet, באות שבשרצים, ba-ot she-ba-sheratzim, a
howler,
a shrieker, or whatever that word means amongst the amongst the rodents.
את אומר באות שבשרצים או אינו אלא באות שבעופות? at omer ba-ot
she-ba-sheratzim o eino ela ba-ot she-ba-ofot? Maybe it's the one of the
birds that has the same name. אמרת צא ולמד מי"ג מידות שהתורה
נדרשת בהן, amarta tze u-lemad mi-yud-gimel middot she-ha-torah nidreshet ba-hen, the thirteen
hermeneutical principles, which is דבר הלמד מעניינו, davar ha-lamed me-inyano, and the
most and the most common one is the issue of context. במאי
קא מדבר בשרצים. be-mai ka medaber be-sheratzim. So this is a context
or the most obvious one or basic one is context and here
it's a list of שרצים. sheratzim. אף כאן בשרצים. af kan be-sheratzim.
So when it says תנשמת tinshemet by birds, it means a bird
תנשמת, tinshemet, and when it says שרצים sheratzim by what do you
call it, when it says תנשמת tinshemet by the שרצים, sheratzim, it
means a שרץ sheretz that's called a תנשמת. tinshemet. What type of
a שרץ sheretz is this? So רש"י Rashi says it's a mole
and therefore that's why he's inclined to say that the what do
you call
it, the bird one is a bat because a bat looks a
little bit like a mole with wings. The
what do you call it, Feliks here has תנשמת tinshemet one being
an owl, which is one translation of רש"י, Rashi, a barn screech
owl. So there's the screeching. And the שרץ sheretz it has as
a chameleon. So why are they both called a תנשמת? tinshemet? There's
the chameleon picture, I don't know if you can see it. There's
the barn screech owl. What's the reason? Let me see the reason
he says that it's called that the גמרא Gemara compares it. First
of all, he gives a whole list of different things that it
says that people say it is: a weasel or a mole, various
things. Ah,
so he says the word תנשמת tinshemet is like from the word
נשמה, neshamah, which has to do with the way it breathes, it
breathes, that
breathes
air
and he takes the translation of באות, ba-ot, which is a way
others translate it, I believe the ערוך, Arukh, that באות ba-ot means
fearful or disgusting and says that these two animals cause repugnance. Of
course, why specifically these two, who knows. Okay, but anyway, so now
we have that there's an animal that's called the תנשמת tinshemet that
is a forbidden type of a flying creature, a bird, and one
that is a forbidden type of a שרץ, sheretz, and they're both
described as באות, ba-ot, whatever that means. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
Let's take a look.
I'm sorry, I just lost the place for a second. Okay,
here we go. So the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says,
באות שבעופות, ba-ot she-ba-ofot, and now אביי Abaye identifies it with words
that were known at his time. What is this bird that is
באות שבעופות, ba-ot she-ba-ofot, the screechy or the repugnant bird? קיפוף. kipuf.
It is a קיפוף, kipuf, which again, either again here for רש"י
Rashi means a bat or a owl.
באות שבשרצים, ba-ot she-ba-sheratzim, and what about the שרצים? sheratzim? קורפדאי, korpadai,
which רש"י Rashi says, as I said, means a mole. אמר רב
יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, קאת, ka'at, זו הקוק. zo ha-kuk. Now we're
back to identifying the biblical bird. So the קאת ka'at is the
קוק kuk or the קיק, kik, some say. I'll tell you again
what Feliks says that means. He says it's a tawny owl.
And רש"י Rashi gives a French explanation, which I don't know what
it means. רחם, racham, what is the רחם? racham? זו שרקרק. zo
sherakrak.
That is the shrieker or the thing called the שרקרק. sherakrak. What
is that example? אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, למה נקרא שמו
רחם? lamah nikra shemo racham? Why is it called the רחם? racham?
כיון שבא רחם באו רחמים לעולם, keivan she-ba racham ba'u rachamim la-olam,
because when the רחם racham comes, it brings compassion to the world.
It is a harbinger, it is a sign of the beginning of
the rainy season. As a result, some have identified it with a
bird called a roller. Again, here Feliks says it's an Egyptian vulture.
But I think some identify it, let me just check here what
Living Torah translates it as.
The magpie. Right, magpie is a common one
and he also said, oh, okay. So anyway,
so magpie is often common
explanation and what's-his-name, the Artscroll brought down a translation explanation that it
was a bird called a roller because רש"י, Rashi, the way in
which רש"י Rashi identifies it. So
and that is also the bird that comes at the beginning of
the rainy season in the land of Israel. So when it comes,
comes compassion to the world. אמר רב ביבי בר אביי, amar Rav
Bibi bar Abaye, והוא דיתיב אמידי ועביד שרק שרק. ve-hu de-yativ a-midi
ve-avid sherak sherak. That's only when it sits on something and does
its crowing, its שרק שרק, sherak sherak, its screeching. דגמירי, de-gemiri,
so that's when it's a sign that rain is coming. דגמירי, de-gemiri,
I'm sorry, I keep on losing the place, right, and we have
a tradition, דגמירי, de-gemiri, דיתיב אארעא ושריק, de-yativ a-ara ve-sharik, if it
actually
sits
on the ground and shrieks.
Rather than sitting on something like a branch, but if it sits
on the ground or maybe sits and rather than stands and shrieks,
אתא משיחא, ata meshikha, then actually it's because it's a harbinger of
compassion, then it's real, and this is an unusual thing for it
to do, that's actually a sign that the משיח Mashiach is going
to come, שנאמר אשרקה להם ואקבצם, shene'emar eshreka lahem v'akabtsem, I will
shriek, I will cry out to them and I will gather them,
says the verse in prophesying the coming of the משיח. Mashiach. So
אמרו ליה רב אדא בר שימי למר בר רב אידי, amru leh
Rav Adda bar Shimi l'Mar bar Rav Idai, so רב אדא בר
שימי Rav Adda bar Shimi said to מר בר רב אידי, Mar
bar Rav Idai, והא ההוא דיתיב בי כרבי ושריק, ve-ha hahu d'yasiv
be-karve v'sharik,
one minute, there was a case of one that sat among the
cabbages and shrieked, ואתא גללא ופצעיה למוחיה v'ata galala u-fats'iyeh le-mocheih and
a boulder came and smashed in its head. So it was quite
different from actually presaging the coming of the משיח. Mashiach. So אמר
ליה, amar leh, he said back, ההוא כדבא הוה, hahu kadba hava,
that was a false messenger, that was a false משיח Mashiach or
a false announcer of the משיח. Mashiach. So how do we know
it was? We know because the boulder came and crashed in its
head. But if no boulder comes and crashes in its head and
it's sitting on the ground and shrieking, then you know it's telling
you that the משיח Mashiach is going to come. Okay, so that
is the רחם. rakham. תנו רבנן עורב זה עורב, Tanu Rabbanan: orev
zeh orev, what's the עורב? orev? The raven or the crow, that's
the עורב. orev. Okay, את כל עורב, et kol orev, every עורב.
orev. So before we had other things yesterday, other things that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer included, but the rabbis disagreed were not included in
the category of עורב. orev. So here we are seeing things that
even the rabbis agree are included in the category of עורב. orev.
So what is that? להביא עורב העמקי, le-havi orev ha-amaki, the one
of the
valleys, למינו, l'mino, according to its kind, להביא עורב הבא בראשי יונים,
le-havi orev ha-ba b'roshey yonim, the עורב orev that comes in the
front of doves. We'll see what that means in a minute, but
it sounds like it leads a flock of doves. אמר מר, Amar
Mar, so we said, so now we're going to analyze this. עורב
זה עורב, Orev zeh orev, that's the עורב. orev. אטו, Atu, says
the גמרא, Gemara, what's going on? קמן קאי? kaman kai? Is it
like in front of us that we can say, oh this is
the עורב, orev, you know, like because since we're distinguishing it from
other עורבים orevim as we do in a minute, the one of
the valleys and so on, you would expect here that it would
tell you what type of עורב orev do we mean, the classic
עורב orev or something of that nature.
So the גמרא Gemara modifies the text, so that's what it means.
Of course in context it probably just means the one that is
most commonly known or most commonly called the עורב, orev, but the
גמרא Gemara feels that here the ברייתא Baraita should have been more
specific because it's distinguishing it from other עורבים. orevim. אלא אימא עורב
זה עורב אוכמא, ella eima orev zeh orev uchma, fine, the עורב
orev is the black עורב, orev, the black crow or raven.
וכן הוא אומר קווצותיו תלתלים שחורות כעורב, v'chen hu omer: kvutsotav taltalim
shechorot ke-orev, his locks are as black as those of a raven.
העמקי חיורא, ha-amaki chivra, the one of the valleys is white or
whitish. וכן הוא אומר ומראהו עמוק מן העור. v'chen hu omer: u-marehu
amok min ha-or. So עמקי amaki here is saying does not mean
valley, the עמק, emek, but deep, and because as a פסוק pasuk
says, which is not really a פסוק, pasuk, but it's a rephrasing
of a פסוק pasuk that the גמרא Gemara does, but in talking
about the spot of leprosy that its appearance is lighter than that
of the skin. And the גמרא Gemara here and רש"י Rashi repeats
and in other places and רש"י Rashi repeats on the תורה Torah
in interpreting certain פסוקים pesukim about the צרעת tsara'at says that the
lighter colors of the צרעת tsara'at appear to be deeper than the
darker ones, which the רמב"ן Ramban asks and is very strange because
it's certainly not our experience if we see something light and dark
side by side, the darker thing seems to us to be deeper
than the lighter thing. So I really don't know an answer to
that, but anyway that's why it's called the deep עורב orev because
it is of a lighter color. כמראה
חמה עמוקה מן הצל,
k'mareh khama
amuka min ha-tsel, so the appearance of this spot of leprosy is
deeper than that of the skin, which means, says the גמרא, Gemara,
the way the appearance of the sun, of like a sunlit sidewalk
imagine, looks deeper than the shade that is nearby it. So
maybe it's a question of background and
foreground, shade looks maybe a little bit more in the foreground, the
lighted sidewalk in the background, although as I said the רמב"ן Ramban
is troubled with that, it does not seem to be our experience.
Okay, ועורב הבא בראשי יונים, v'orev ha-ba b'roshey yonim, now what is
the עורב orev that goes at the head of doves?
אמר רב פפא לא תימא דאתי בראשי יוני, Amar Rav Pappa: lo
tema d'atey be-roshey yonei, it doesn't mean it flies at the head
of a flock of
doves, אלא דדמי רישיה ליונה, ella d'dami reshey l'yona, its head looks
somewhat like that of a dove. Okay, so that is the עורב,
orev, we know the עורב orev is the raven or the crow,
I don't know are the raven and the crow the same thing,
I must say I am not really sure, but anyway
let me see what he says. He says it means, okay, my
son tells me that a raven and crows are not the same
thing, except Feliks here says that he translates one of them as
an עורב אפור, orev afur, hooded crow, and the other as an
עורב שחור, orev shachor, raven. So they certainly are related. And maybe
that's exactly why here the גמרא Gemara describing these two עורבים, orevim,
maybe exactly that of a, of a, of a crow and raven.
Maybe that's also the, you know, the ones that have more white
in them. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so, תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הנץ, Hanetz, what is the הנץ? Netz? So זה
הנץ, Ze Hanetz, that's what we know is the הנץ. Netz. That's
helpful. So again, what here, it's the sparrowhawk according
to Felix. So that is the הנץ, Netz, זה הנץ, Ze Netz,
למינהו להביא את בר
חוריה, L'minehu l'havi et bar chirya, למינהו, l'minehu, its species includes something
called בר חוריה Bar Chirya which is a related species to the
הנץ. Netz. So מאי בר חוריה, Mai Bar Chirya, what is the
בר חוריה? Bar Chirya? אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: שורינקא. shurinka. Okay, something
called a שורינקא, shurinka, which again was known to them. אמר רב
יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: החסידה, Hachasida, what is the חסידה? Chasida? זו
דיה לבנה. Zu daya levana. That is the white דיה, daya, and
this is going to lead into the rest of today's דף daf
where we actually identify some of the words in the list in
the תורה Torah are really referring to the same type of animal.
So the גמרא Gemara does refer to a דיה, daya, which we
will get to, and now he is saying the חסידה Chasida is
the white דיה. daya. So what is that, and what is the
דיה? daya? So again, just going here by Felix, he says the
חסידה, Chasida, the white חסידה Chasida is the stork. And the
דיה daya doesn't tell you, doesn't have here what the דיה daya
is. Okay, so anyway, he says that it is the stork.
The איה, aya, which the גמרא Gemara does compare to the דיה,
daya, oh here, דאה דיה. da'a daya. So he, so Felix assumes
that דאה da'a and דיה daya are the same, and he says
it's a black kite, which has nothing to do with a stork.
So
and איה aya is, which we'll see in a minute, is a
buzzard. So anyway, okay, so here he says that this is the
white דיה, daya, which is where it could mean the stork, but
again it's a question about what you assume the דיה daya means.
Let's keep on going.
זו דיה לבנה. Zu daya levana. למה נקרא שמה חסידה? Lama nikra
shema chasida? Why is it called a חסידה? Chasida? שעושה חסידות עם
חברותיה. She'osa chasidut im chavroteha. Because it does kindness with its friend,
it shares its food with its friends. There is a very common
מוסר שמועס mussar shmuess or whatever, or דבר תורה dvar Torah that
says, how is it if we assume that the reason that these
birds are not כשר kosher is because they're birds of prey and
they represent evil, so how come this bird, which is even called
kindness and חסידה Chasida and shares its food with its friends, how
come it is a forbidden bird? And the answer given is because
it only shares it with its friends. It does not share it
with those that are not its friends. So that is not true
kindness, in a way it could almost be self-interest.
Okay. האנפה, Ha'anafa, what is the אנפה? Anafa? זו דיה רגזנית. Zu
daya ragzanit. That is the angry דיה. daya.
So and whatever the דיה daya is, this one was the white
one and this one was the angry one. ולמה נקרא שמה אנפה?
V'lama nikra shema anafa? Why is it called אנפה? Anafa? שמנאפת עם
חברותיה. Shemna'efet im chavroteha. So again, there's a word here, a question
about what the גירסא girsa is. It makes more sense the גירסא
girsa שמנאנפת, shemna'anefet, אלף נון, alef nun, which is the word
אנפה, anafa, ואנף v'anaf means to be angry. התאנף בי, Hitanef bi,
God got angry with me, says משה Moshe a few פרשיות parshiyot
ago. So he gets angry with his friends. Our גירסא girsa of
מנאפת mna'efet would mean that it commits adultery, and there definitely are
birds that do that as well,
where we get the phrase I think henpecked from. Anyway, so anyway,
but one or the other, that is this word that is, that
is this bird that is the אנפה. Anafa. אמר רב חנן בר
רב חסדא אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav Chanan bar Rav Chisda amar
Rav Chisda. So רב חנן בר רב חסדא Rav Chanan bar Rav
Chisda says in the name of his father רב חסדא. Rav Chisda.
אמר רב חנן בריה דרבא אמר רב. Amar Rav Chanan brei d'Rava
amar Rav. All of this in the name of רב. Rav. עשרים
וארבעה עופות טמאים הן. Esrim v'arba'ah ofot tme'im hen. There are twenty-four,
which we have been saying all along in the גמרא, Gemara, and
now we are going to get down, since now that we've done
the best we could to identify what's on the list, now we're
going to get down to counting the number and seeing how it
equals to be twenty-four, and as a result conflating certain things on
the list. So let's take a look. There are twenty-four. אמר ליה
רב חנן
בר רב חסדא לרב חסדא. Amar lei Rav Chanan bar Rav Chisda
l'Rav Chisda. So רב חנן, Rav Chanan, the son of רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, so the one who said this tradition over in the
name of his father, so his father taught it to him, רב
חסדא. Rav Chisda. So now he turns back and he asks his
father, והיכא? v'heicha? How do you get twenty-four? Where do you see
a list of twenty-four? אי בויקרא עשרין הוו. Ei b'Vayikra esrin havu.
If you count the number of words in ויקרא, Vayikra, you'll get
twenty. אי במשנה תורה עשרין וחדא הוו. Ei b'Mishneh Torah esrin v'chada
havu. If it's in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah which we just read
yesterday,
it's twenty-one. You can't get to twenty-four. וכי תימא דאה דכתיבא בויקרא
ולא כתיבא במשנה תורה.
V'chi teima da'ah d'chtiva b'Vayikra v'lo chtiva
b'Mishneh Torah. So there's one word bird דאה, da'ah, which is in
ויקרא Vayikra and it's not in משנה תורה. Mishneh Torah. So let's
add those together. So let's add that to the list in משנה
תורה. Mishneh Torah. שדי עלייהו. Shadi aleihu. You add it to the
twenty-one in משנה תורה. Mishneh Torah. אכתי עשרין ותרין הוו. Achati esrin
v'trein havu. You're only up to twenty-two, you're not up to twenty-four.
אמר ליה. Amar lei. So he says back to him, הכי אמר
אבוה דאמך משמיה דרב. Hachi amar avuha d'imach mishme d'Rav. Here is
what your father's mother... my mother-in-law, your grand, my father-in-law, excuse me,
your grandfather said in the name of רב *Rav*, who was this
by the way רש''י Rashi *Rashi* says this was רב חנן בר
אבא *Rav Chanan bar Abba* בר רבה *bar Rabba* was his grandfather
and רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*'s father-in-law. So here's what he said in
the name of רב *Rav*, למינהו l'minu למינהו l'minu למינהו l'minu *leminehu
leminehu leminehu*, if you look in ויקרא Vayikra, *Vayikra* and למינהו l'minu
*leminehu* it says למינהו l'minu למינהו *leminehu leminehu* four times. It's actually
quite interesting here that the תולדות אהרן *Toldot Aharon* quotes three from
ויקרא Vayikra. *Vayikra* and one from דברים Devarim, *Devarim* because actually as
we're going to see we do some conflating with the ones in
ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra*. So more significantly if you count those in דברים
Devarim, *Devarim*, it says למינהו למינהו *leminehu leminehu* four times. So all
in דברים Devarim, *Devarim* you have four למינהוס *leminehus*. So הרי כאן
ארבע *harei kan arba*, that's four. So that adds as we've seen
until now that there are other species that are considered to be
of extended species that are included. So you have 20 base plus
the four למינהו *leminehu* extended species and that's how you get 24.
אי הכי *ei hachi*, if that's true, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
עשרין ושיתא הוו *esrim v'shita havvei*, it's not 24, it's 26 because
we just said that there are 21 in דברים Devarim *Devarim*. You
add one from ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra* you get 22 and then you
have the למינהוס *leminehus* you're up to 26. So
how are you going to get till 24? So let's take a
look. אמר אביי Abaye *amar Abaye* דאה Da וראה אחת היא
*da'ah v'ra'ah achat hi*. So now is what we start conflating and
saying certain birds are the same. Now we're going to sometimes say
that the ויקרא Vayikra. *Vayikra* and דברים Devarim, *Devarim* when the list
differ you really don't add them together, they're really different names of
the same birds, but sometimes we're even going to conflate two birds
that are in the same list and say that they are really
just different names of the same bird. And the reason interestingly why
we're going to say that the תורה Torah *Torah* gives you different
names is that people should not get confused and say oh the
תורה Torah, *Torah* only made the דאה Da. *da'ah* forbidden, it didn't
make the ראה Ra, *ra'ah* forbidden, so it gives you both names.
So interestingly למינהו *leminehu* includes a different species in terms of our
list of getting to 24
but actual different names might actually be referring to the same species
and that's going to we're going to conflate them in order to
keep our list of 24. So now it's important to know how
these lists differ in ויקרא Vayikra. *Vayikra* and in דברים Devarim *Devarim*.
A little רש''י *Rashi* here at the very first wide line says
בספר ויקרא Vayikra *b'sefer Vayikra* at the very last narrow line כתיב
ואת הדאה ואת האיה למינה ve'es ha'da'ah ve'es ha'ayah le'minah. *ktiv v'et
ha'da'ah v'et ha'ayah l'minah*. So in ויקרא Vayikra. *Vayikra* you have דאה
da'ah *da'ah* and איה Aya, *ayah* and משנה תורה Mishneh Torah *Mishneh
Torah* it says ראה Ra איה Aya ודיה למינה le'minah *ra'ah ayah
v'dayah l'minah*. So that's a little confusing. Okay, so what do you
have? Try to line them up. You had in one you have
דאה da'ah, *da'ah* and איה Aya *ayah*, A and B, דאה da'ah
*da'ah* and איה Aya *ayah*. The other you have ראה Ra *ra'ah*
so consider ראה ra'ah. *ra'ah* on this bottom list that's underneath the
other words. So דאה da'ah *da'ah* and איה Aya *ayah* and underneath
you have ראה ra'ah *ra'ah* very much like דאה da'ah, *da'ah* except
with a ר *resh*. ראה ra'ah *ra'ah* and איה ayah *ayah* and
then you have a totally new
one דייה dayah *dayah*. Okay, so it's important think of it that
way graphically visually because that'll help seeing how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
combines them. So the first answer is so we have to get
from 26 down to 24 so we're going to have to combine
two things not just one thing. So let's see again אביי Abaye
*Abaye*'s answer. אמר אביי Abaye *amar Abaye* דאה da'ah וראה אחת היא
*da'ah v'ra'ah achat hi*. So that's the easiest, right? It's the same
place in the list, one says דאה da'ah *da'ah* and איה Aya.
*ayah* the other says ראה ra'ah *ra'ah* איה aya. *ayah*. It's a
difference of a ד *dalet* and a ר *resh* and therefore those
are really the same species. So you really have only 25 not
26. אי סלקא דעתך תרתי אינון *ei salka deitach tarti inun* if
you think like we said before that they are two species so
that can't be. Why can't it be? Because says the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* מכדי michdi, *michdi* let's see. משנה תורה לאוסופי הוא דאתא Mishneh
Torah l'osufé hu d'asa. *Mishneh Torah l'osufi hu d'ata* when משה *Moshe*
says things in דברים Devarim *Devarim* he the list is coming to
add to what you have in ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra*. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* takes this as a principle and not necessarily in all of
משנה תורה Mishneh Torah *Mishneh Torah* but at least when it comes
to this list that it is going to have everything it said
in ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra* plus more, so it can't have less than
the list in ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra*. So if that's true מאי שנא
הכא דכתיב דאה mai shena hacha d'khtiv da'ah? מאי שנא הכא דכתיב
ראה ra'ah *mai shna hacha d'ktiv da'ah mai shna hacha d'ktiv ra'ah*?
Why in the one list it says דאה da'ah? *da'ah* and the
other ראה ra'ah *ra'ah*? You can't say that the דברים Devarim *Devarim*
list does not have something in the list of ויקרא Vayikra. *Vayikra*
that goes against this principle. אלא שמע מינה ela shma mina, ראה
ra'ah ודאה אחת היא *ela shma mina ra'ah v'da'ah achat hi*. So
in order to explain that the דברים Devarim *Devarim* list does not
have something less than the
ויקרא Vayikra. *Vayikra* list we have to say that דאה da, *da'ah*
and ראה ra'ah *ra'ah* are the same. So again in ויקרא Vayikra.
*Vayikra* you have דאה da *da'ah* and איה aya, *ayah* here you
have ראה ra'ah *ra'ah* איה aya, *ayah* and דייה dayah *dayah*. So
ראה ra'ah *ra'ah* and דאה da *da'ah* which are one on top
of the other and almost the same word those are really the
same species. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not happy ואכתי עשרים
וחמש הוו *v'achati esrim v'chamesh havvei* you're still only 25 we have
to get down to 24 so you have to essentially conflate yet
another species. So
אמר אביי *amar Abaye* כשם שראה ודאה אחת היא *keshem she'ra'ah v'da'ah
achat hi* the same way we lined
so the איה aya, and the דיה Daya are the same species.
Now that's a bigger חידוש Chiddush because that is listed in the
same list. It says in דברים, Devarim? it says, you know, דא,
Da, ראה, ra'ah and excuse me, דא, Da, איה, aya, and דיה.
Daya. So איה aya and דיה Daya are on the same list,
but אביי is saying again, the words sound very similar and they
are essentially the same bird with different names, even though they are
exactly in the same list. The תורה's Torah giving you two different
names. So what we've done is we've conflated ראה ra'ah and דאה
da from two different lists. The one is on top of the
other, they're basically the same word, they're the same. And then within
the same list in דברים, Devarim איה aya and דיה Daya were
also conflated. Now how do we know this? דאי סלקא דעתך תרתי
אינון, de'isalka dach'tach tarti inun, if you say that they're two, מכדי,
michtiv, משנה תורה Mishneh Torah, לאסופי הוא דאתא. le'asofei hu de'ata. So
משנה תורה Torah comes to add. Well, good, it does add. Here
it says both איה aya, and דיה. Daya. But no, we have
a question. מאי שנא הכא דכתיב למינה אאיה? mai shena hacha d'chsiv
le'minah a'aya?
Here in דברים, Devarim it says by the איה aya. ואת האיה
למינה. ve'es ha'ayah le'minah. ומאי שנא התם דכתיב למינה אדיה? u'mai shena
hasam d'chsiv le'minah a'dayah? And
over there it says למינה le'minah. by the דיה. Daya. Let me
just, excuse me, get a חומש Chumash to confirm which is which,
if I get a little bit confused here.
So in the list of שמיני, Shemini, it says ואת הדאה ואת
האיה למינה. le'minah
So there's דיה dayah and איה Aya למינה. le'minah.
And in משנה תורה, where we read yesterday,
excuse me, just one second,
oh here it is, והראה ואת האיה והדיה למינה. ve'ha'ra'ah ve'es ha'ayah
ve'ha'dayah le'minah.
So here it says דיה למינה. dayah le'minah. Now of course, just
so you know, the way the פסוקים pesukim are written, למינה le'minah
always only appears at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. But nevertheless,
so it's because it here says דיה dayah at the end, it
adds דיה dayah and it says למינה. le'minah So that's why it
says it by the דיה. dayah. But the גמרא Gemara assumes as
we said that למינה le'minah has very specific Halachic meaning, that the
things that it says למינה le'minah come to broaden that species. So
now we've got a problem. מאי שנא הכא דכתיב למינה אאיה? mai
shena hacha d'chsiv le'minah a'aya? Over there in ויקרא, Vayikra it says
למינה le'minah by the איה. Aya ומאי שנא התם, u'mai shena hasam,
and in דברים Devarim where it adds the word דיה, dayah, דכתיב
למינה אדיה, d'chsiv le'minah a'dayah, it says למינה le'minah by דיה, dayah,
but it doesn't have it by איה. ayah. So that's coming to
have it has less than you had in ויקרא. Vayikra. ויקרא Vayikra
had the למינה le'minah by the איה, ayah it was a broader
category. And in דברים, Devarim it doesn't say the word דיה dayah
by... it doesn't say the word למינה l'mina its species by איה,
ayah which seems to be a smaller group, and that violates our
principle. So אלא שמע
מינה איה ודיה אחת היא. ella shma mina aya ve'daya achas hi.
So they're really the same, and since they're really the same, so
it's not a problem that it doesn't say למינה by one of
them in דברים Devarim because it says it by the other and
they both are really the same. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says וכי מאחר דאיה ודיה אחת היא, ve'chi me'achar de'aya ve'daya achas
hi, if they're really the same, למה ליה למכתב איה ודיה, lama
lei limichtav aya ve'daya, why does it say both? And you know,
it's more of a question here because it's on the same list.
It's less of a question between ויקרא Vayikra and דברים Devarim where,
okay, one place it calls it one, one place the other thing.
But here it's the same list. Why say, use two words to
describe the same thing? So כדתניא, k'detanya, like we taught in the
ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, רבי Rebbi says, אקרא אני איה,
ekra ani aya, דיה למה נאמר? dayah lama ne'emar? It already had
said איה, ayah. why did it have to say דיה dayah if
it's essentially the same thing, which is exactly what אביי just said.
Now we see that רבי Rebbi is saying it. כדי שלא תתן
פתחון פה לבעל דין לחלוק, kedei she'lo titen pitchon peh l'ba'al din
lachlok, so you should not give an opening for somebody who would
wanted to like make a distinction or to disagree. שלא תהא אחת
קורא איה והוא קורא דיה, she'lo tehei achas korei aya ve'hu korei
dayah, everybody calls a certain bird an
איה, ayah and he says, you know, that's not an איה ayah,
that is forbidden in
תורה, excuse me, אתה קורא איה והוא קורא דיה, ata korei aya
ve'hu korei dayah, or אתה קורא דיה והוא קורא איה. ata korei
dayah ve'hu korei aya. You call it one thing, he calls it
the other thing, and he'll tell you this is not what the
תורה forbids, this is only an איה ayah and the תורה only
forbade a דיה dayah or vice versa. So therefore, לכך כתב במשנה
תורה והראה ואת האיה והדיה למינה. lechach kasav b'Mishneh Torah ve'ha'ra'ah ve'es
ha'ayah ve'ha'dayah le'minah. It added the word דיה, dayah, and because a
דיה dayah is really the same as an איה, ayah it just
wanted to clarify that דיה dayah was no different than an איה.
ayah. So what we have done here interestingly is, on the one
hand you could say what we've done is like just, you know,
some
some acrobatics to get us to twenty-four. But if you actually think
about it, the goal of this really has also been, or the
effect of this has been, to
to eliminate the differences between the list in דברים Devarim and the
list in ויקרא. Vayikra One of the differences was ראה ra'ah and
דאה. da So we said fine, it's not a difference, they're basically
the same bird. The other difference was איה ayah and דיה. Daya.
The word איה ayah was added. to the list from or the
word דייה dayah was added, I'm sorry, I got confused again.
The word דייה dayah was added to in the list in דברים
Devarim and we said fine, it's really the same bird as the
איה. ayah, Now once we conflate those, now we have 20 base
birds, 4 למינה and we're back to 24. Okay, back to the
גמרא. Gemara
Okay, מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you on this: למה נשנו בבהמה מפני
השסועה? lama nishnu b'behema mipnei ha-shisua? Why did the Torah repeat the
list in דברים? Devarim So by the mammals it repeated it because
of this new animal called the שסועה. shisua. You remember that was
a דרשה drasha earlier where it said these are the things you
cannot eat from the animals with split hooves, השסועה, ha-shisua, which פשט
pshat means just split hoof, but the גמרא Gemara, said that it's
actually a particular type of an animal, a new animal that is
forbidden. So that's why the list was repeated by the mammals. ובעופות
u'ba-ophos and by birds, why was it repeated? מפני הראה, mipnei ha-ra'ah,
because of the ראה. ra'ah So that that was not mentioned in
the list in ויקרא. Vayikra ויקרא Vayikra, is דאה da and here
it says ראה ra'ah to add that. So it sounds like this
is actually an additional bird, it's not just a different word for
the same bird. מאי לאו מדבהמה דהתם לאוסופי? mai lav mi-de-behema de-hasam
l'osufé? Since by the case of the mammals we said it was
literally adding an animal, this animal called the שסועה, shisua, עופות נמי
לאוסופי? ophos nami l'osufé? So when it comes to the birds as
well, it's literally adding an animal, and this ראה ra'ah is a
new type of a new species that is spelled in דברים Devarim
is forbidden, which was not in ויקרא. Vayikra So the גמרא Gemara
says: לא, התם לאוסופי הכא לפרושי. lo, hasam l'osufé hacha l'fruishe. No,
by mammals it was literally adding an animal that was
forbidden; here it was coming to explicate and here it was coming
to say that you know, although in ויקרא Vayikra it's called a
דאה, da here it's a ראה raah. and it's really the same
bird. So again we are choosing to eliminate any of the differences
between ויקרא Vayikra. and דברים Devarim by saying ראה raah and דאה
da are the same, and איה ayah, and דייה dayah are the
same. Okay, ופליגא דרבי אבהו, upliga de-Rabbi Abbahu, and this argues on
רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. דאמר רבי אבהו, de'amar Rabbi Abbahu, because רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abbahu said: ראה זו איה. ra'ah zu ayah. Rather than
saying איה ayah and דייה daya are the same, he is saying
the ראה raah is the same as the איה. ayah Now hold
on,
right. So again the פסוק pasuk in דברים Devarim is ראה ואת
האיה ואת הדייה למינה. ra'ah v'es ha-ayah v'es ha-dayah l'mina. So he,
we had combined the איה aya and the דייה daya in the
same list; he says the ראה raah and the איה, aya A
and B, the first two of that list in דברים Devarim are
combined. The ראה raah and the איה aya. are the same. ולמה
נקרא שמה ראה? v'lama nikra shema ra'ah? Why is it called a
ראה raah if it's really an איה aya he assumes is its
proper name? שרואה ביותר, she-ro'ah b'yoser, because it can see at a
great distance. וכן הוא אומר, v'chein hu omer, the פסוק pasuk says:
נתיב לא ידעו עיט ולא שזפתו עין איה. nesiv lo yedo'o ayit
v'lo shezafatto ein ayah. A path that was not known by the
עיט, ayit, by like the vulture, and did not, was not peered
upon by the eye of the איה. aya So you see it
uses in this imagery the איה aya like can see from very
far away. So איה aya and ראה raah are the same. So
again the list in דברים Devarim, is ראה איה דייה. ra'ah ayah
dayah. We had combined איה דייה. ayah dayah. He is combining the
first two of the list, ראה raah. and איה, aya because of
its ability to see from far away. תנא, tana, we taught in
a ברייתא: braisa: עומדת בבבל ורואה נבילה בארץ ישראל. omedes b'Bavel v'ro'ah
neveilah b'Eretz Yisrael. This is a bird of prey, a vulture, and
it sees so far that it can be standing in בבל Bavel
and see a carcass all the way in the land of ישראל
Yisrael and swoop down and eat from it. Certainly, you know, we
know birds of prey that fly very, very high and can, you
know, detect a carcass from very low down and swoop down seemingly
out of nowhere when an animal dies in order to eat from
the carcass. Okay, so now we're going to analyze this statement of
רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. So let's take a look. מדראה היינו איה,
mi-de-ra'ah hainu ayah, since a ראה raah is an איה, aya, מכלל
דדאה לאו היינו ראה. miklal di-da'ah lav hainu ra'ah. So we're assuming
right that if he recategorizes, he recategorizes in multiple ways. So we
have our list of ראה איה דייה. ra'ah ayah dayah. We had
before said ראה raah, and דאה da from דברים Devarim, to ויקרא
Vayikra were the same. He is now saying no, ראה raah and
איה aya
are the same. So presumably he's not combining ראה raah, with דאה,
da which is in ויקרא. Vayikra So מכלל דדאה לאו היינו ראה.
miklal di-da'ah lav hainu ra'ah. So the ראה raah is compared to,
is now part of איה aya all in the same list in
דברים Devarim and it's not going to be linked up to the
דאה over there in ויקרא.
מכדי, let's take a look, we can't allow that. משנה תורה לאוסופי
הוא דאתא.
דברים Devarim, is coming to add things to the list, meaning everything
in דברים Devarim, we're assuming that the list in דברים Devarim.
completely includes the list in ויקרא. So מאי שנא הכא דכתיב דאה?
So how do you explain that over in ויקרא it says דאה
ומאי שנא התם דלא כתיב דאה? u-mai shena hasam d'lo khtiv da'ah?
And over there in דברים Devarim? it doesn't say דאה? We cannot
allow that the list in דברים Devarim has less in it than
the list in ויקרא. אלא שמע מינה, shema mina, you must say
even within רבי אבהו... Rabbi Abbahu... דאה וראה ואיה אחת היא da
v'ra v'aya achas hi that they are all the same, cause one
of the differences that we had from ויקרא to דברים Devarim you'll
remember is one said דאה, one said ראה. We assumed that רב
אבהו Rebbe Avahu has to reconcile that as well and has to
reconcile that in a similar way. So now what he's done is
he said ראה and איה aya are the same, that was not
getting rid of a problem because there was no problem between ויקרא
and דברים, Devarim but he was choosing to say ראה and איה
aya are the same, and he's also based on our principle that
you can't have anything in ויקרא that's not in דברים, Devarim he's
saying that דאה and ראה are the same. Now again remember also
in ויקרא it was דאה and איה. aya So now we are
saying that all four of these are all the same, דאה and
איה aya. the same, ראה and איה aya, the same, ראה and
דאה are the same, all four of these are really just one
bird. Okay, so,
and now the only one we're left is the outlier is the
new one of the דייה daya mentioned in דברים and we will
get to that. Okay, so let's go on back, go back, go
back.
ומי דראה היינו איה מכלל דדייה לאו היינו איה. u'mi d'raah hainu
aya mikhlal d'daya lav hainu aya. So now we're going to say,
ah, so now we're going to have to assume that since the
ראה and the איה aya and the דאה and the איה aya.
are all the same bird, so the דייה daya. which is again
the bird added in, let me just make sure I got this
right,
yeah, the דייה daya. which is the word added in, in דברים,
that is not the איה because presumably we're not going to assume
that things are the same unless we're forced to. But now we
have a problem. מאי שנא התם דכתיב למינהו ואת האיה ומאי שנא
הכא דלא כתיב למינהו ואת האיה. mai sh'na hasam d'ksiv l'minu v'es
ha'aya u'mai sh'na hacha d'lo ksiv l'minu v'es ha'aya. The problem that
אביי introduced earlier, right, which is that over in דברים, over in
ויקרא, it says למינהו which is a broadening word by the איה,
and here it says למינהו only by the דייה. daya And again
we cannot have the list in ויקרא to be bigger than the
list in דברים. So how could it say למינהו by the איה
in ויקרא and not say it here in דברים? אלא אדאיה ולא
כתיב למינהו אאיה אלא אדייה Ela ad'aya v'lo ksiv l'minu a'aya ela
ad'daya and it only says it on the דייה. daya אלא שמע
מינה דאה וראה ודייה ואיה אחת היא. Ela shma mina da v'raah
v'daya v'aya achas hi. They're all the same. Okay, so what have
we said? Basically, it was pretty confusing but let's just repeat it
again.
We're basically working by the principle that the list in דברים can
be, has to have everything in the list of ויקרא. One thing
it doesn't have, and we're also trying to
just avoid contradictions or whatever,
reconcile anything that's not exactly the same. So the list in ויקרא
had דאה whereas that was not in the list in דברים and
in its place it had ראה. So that led to the key
statement that ראה and דאה are the same. The list in ויקרא
had למינהו by the איה and the list in דברים only had
the למינהו by the דייה daya and didn't have it by the
איה which made the איה a smaller category. So to solve that
problem, we said איה and דייה daya. were the same. And the
גמרא Gemara, is going to assume that everybody has to buy into
those assumptions, everybody has to buy into those two ways of conflating
it. So you do it that way out of all of these,
you have basically three birds. You have the ראה, the, excuse me,
you have two birds. You have the ראה and you have the
איה. The דייה is part of the איה, the דאה is part
of the ראה, you have two birds. But then and everybody buys
into those assumptions, but then comes רב אבהו, Rebbe Avahu, he says
the ראה slash דאה is the same as the איה slash דייה.
And he puts all those two things all together so what started
off as four, according to the גמרא Gemara, became two, and now
according to רב אבהו Rebbe Avahu all become one. So רב אבהו
Rebbe Avahu disagrees with our statement before and would not have a
list of twenty-four birds but only of twenty-three birds. Okay, let's continue.
Okay. תניא, Tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Braisa, איסי בן יהודה
אומר מאה עופות טמאים יש במזרח וכולן מין איה הן. Isi ben
Yehuda omer meah ofos t'meiyim yesh b'mizrach v'chulan min aya hen. There
are a hundred species of non-kosher birds in the east and they're
all variations of the איה. תני, Tani, we taught in a ברייתא,
Braisa, אבימי בריה דרבי אבהו, Avimi breih d'Rebbe Avahu, אבימי Avimi the
son of רב אבהו, Rebbe Avahu, שבע מאה מיני דגים הם, shiva
meah minei dagim hem, there are seven hundred species of fish, and
these sound to us to be exaggerations but anybody who has studied
anything
about science and taxonomy and biology whatever you know that there's you
know that there are hundreds sometimes thousands of species of a given
types of animals. So he says there are seven hundred types of
fish, ושמונה מאה מיני חגבים, u'shmonah meah minei chagavim,
and eight hundred types of grasshoppers, ולאופות אין מספר, v'la'ofos ein mispar,
and
birds infinite, no number. Now presumably he means non-kosher. Seven hundred types
of non-kosher fish, eight hundred types of non-kosher grasshoppers, and an innumerable
type of non-kosher birds. So the גמרא says עופות כד הוי? Ofos
kad havi? What do you mean? We just got through proving that
there are twenty-four species of non-kosher birds. אלא ולאופות טהורים אין מספר.
Ela v'la'ofos tehorim ein mispar. No, no, kosher birds are without number,
right? The non-kosher... only 24, the kosher are innumerable because they're however
many species there are outside of those 24. And if that's true,
by the way, it's also not clear whether when he's saying the
700 and 800 by the fish and the grasshoppers, maybe they also,
he means the kosher ones. Let's take a look. תניא ותנא בברייתא,
Tanya v'tana b'braisa, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, גלוי וידוע. Galui v'yadua. Rashi
basically says this next גמרא, he pretty much distills it on his
commentary in דברים which we just read yesterday. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer,
גלוי וידוע לפני מי שאמר והיה העולם, Galui v'yadua lifnei mi she'amar
v'hayah ha'olam, it is revealed before the one who said and created
the world, before God, שבהמה טמאה מרובה מן הטהורה, she'beheimah tmeiah merubah
min hatehorah, that there were many more non-kosher species of mammals than
kosher. לפיכך מנה הכתוב בטהורה, Lefichach manah hakatuv batehorah, therefore the Torah
lists the kosher ones because it's going to give you the shorter
list, meaning he's dealing with a problem of why does the Torah
list the kosher mammals and it lists the non-kosher birds. And the
reason is it gives you the shorter of the two lists. So
since there are many more non-kosher mammals, it lists the kosher ones.
And also גלוי וידוע לפני מי שאמר והיה העולם, Galui v'yadua lifnei
mi she'amar v'hayah ha'olam, it's known to God שעופות טהורים מרובים על
הטמאים, she'ofos tehorim merubim al hatme'im, that there are many, many more
kosher species of birds than non-kosher. לפיכך מנה הכתוב בטמאים, Lefichach manah
hakatuv batme'im, and it only gave you the list of the non-kosher.
מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? So what's the point of telling
us this? Well, one thing it's telling us is explaining why the
lists, one is kosher, one is non-kosher, but what do we learn
from it? כי דרב הונא אמר רב, Ki d'Rav Huna amar Rav,
like Rav Huna said in the name of Rav. דאמר רב הונא
אמר רב ואמרי לה אמר רב הונא אמר רב משום רבי מאיר,
D'amar Rav Huna amar Rav v'amri lah amar Rav Huna amar Rav
mishum Rebbi Meir, some say he says in the name of Rabbi
Meir, לעולם ישנה אדם לתלמידו דרך קצרה, Le'olam yishaneh adam l'talmido derech
ktzarah, one should always try to teach your students the shortest way
possible. So if God wants to give us a list, He'll give
us the shorter list and we will infer that everything not on
the list is forbidden or is permissible based on which type of
list it is. אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, now Rav Yitzchak
says עוף טהור נאכל במסורת, Of tahor ne'echal b'mesores, you can eat
kosher birds based on tradition. As he says, this is not saying
you need a tradition, it is saying a tradition suffices. If you
don't know about the, you know, about whether it has the סימנים
simanim or it has some kosher and some non-kosher סימנים simanim and
you need to know if it's on the list, right? All of
this is coming in the context of which are the birds on
the list. With חז"ל Chazal having spent the last two days telling
us a lot of identifying of this is this species, this is
that species, but we don't know what they're talking about and they
maybe, you know, there were people at that time that didn't always
know which every species was. So how do you know if it
has some kosher and some non-kosher סימנים simanim if it's on the
list? And the answer is you can rely on a tradition. So
here he's saying a tradition suffices. This becomes in later, you know,
later times like in רש"י and, you know, amongst some commentators, not
only that a tradition suffices but a tradition is necessary. But here
in the גמרא it's saying that a tradition suffices. Now, נאמן הצייד
לומר עוף זה טיהר לי רבי, Ne'eman hatzayad lomar of zeh tiher
li rabbi,
a hunter is believed to say that this is a kosher species
of bird that my master taught me. So אמר רבי יוחנן והוא
שבקי בהן ובשמותיהן. Amar Rebbi Yochanan v'hu shebaki bahen uvishmoseihen. You have
to know both, you know, that that person, that רבי Rebbi that
gave you this tradition knew what the birds looked like and also
knew their names. Again, the purpose of names, what we said earlier,
was because if something is called the name of a particular non-kosher
species, even if it may be really appears to be kosher, maybe
because of the name we have to be concerned that it might
be, might be an extension, an extended species of the non-kosher species.
But if you know its name and you know what it looks
like and you have a tradition, so you know, so it's not
just and this also, by the way, is very important, right? Because
sometimes people just know things like בעל פה ba'al peh orally, but
they never are in touch with the actual facts on the ground
and therefore a lot of confusion and, you know, ultimately gets introduced
and inaccuracy gets introduced into the tradition. But if you know exactly
the animal you're talking about and you know what it's
called and you have a tradition about it that it's kosher, then
it's fine. Let's just read one more line and we'll wrap up
for today. בעי רבי זירא, Ba'ei Rebbi Zeira, Rabbi Zeira asked רבו
חכם או רבו צייד? Rabbo chacham o rabbo tzayad? When it says
you can trust the tradition, does it mean the tradition of your,
of your teacher? Does it mean your teacher who is your hunter
teacher or your, or your רבי Rebbi teacher, your Torah teacher? Because
you're saying a hunter comes with a tradition from his teacher.
So תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דאמר רבי יוחנן והוא
שבקי בהן ובשמותיהן, d'amar Rebbi Yochanan v'hu shebaki bahen uvishmoseihen, you know
them and their names. אי אמרת בשלמא רבו צייד, Ei amart bishlama
rabbo tzayad, if you're talking about a hunter, your master hunter taught
you this, שפיר, shapir, I understand that he knows birds and he
knows what the species are called. אלא אי אמרת רבו חכם, Ela
ei amart rabbo chacham, if it is your teacher who's a Torah
teacher, בשלמא שמהא גמר להו, bishlama shemaha gmar lehu, I understand that
he can know a name, he can have traditions about names, אלא
אינהו מי ידע? ela inhu mi yada? Since when do Torah teachers
know what birds look like and really have a strong knowledge of,
you know, about the realities of birds? Which is quite fascinating given
the whole earlier גמרא, but note that the earlier גמרא, a lot
of it was saying oh this is this, this is this, a
lot of it might of been traditions about the names, but you
did not have a very detailed discussion about the realities, the physical
realities, you know, or of the bird. So since when do we
assume that the חכמים Chachamim know about all those realities of birds?
So אלא לאו שמע מינה רבו צייד. ela lav shema mina rabo
tzayad. You see with me when you have even a tradition, even
a tradition that comes from his master the hunter, שמע מינה, that
is that is that is a good proof, which is quite fascinating,
something we might not have expected, that if you have a tradition
that comes from, you know, a פרום frum Jew even if not
a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, even if not a rabbi, even if
not a sage, but it's a tradition of somebody who really knew
what he was talking about and he had a tradition. He's not
sort of determining that it is כשר, kosher, he has a tradition
that it is כשר, kosher, which comes from earlier generations, that tradition
is a sufficient basis for assuming that it is not the bird
on the list. So now we know that four כשר kosher סימנים
simanim determine it's כשר, kosher, a tradition, less than that it might
still be כשר kosher if it's not on the list, and a
tradition is sufficient for determining it's כשר. kosher. And as we saw
yesterday, however, רש״י Rashi says because you can't always know if a
bird is a bird of prey or not, we not only is
a tradition sufficient, but a tradition is actually necessary. To be continued
tomorrow, God willing in person. Please stay safe during the storm. Be
well.